Finding Aid for Horace L. Wilgus Papers, 1878-1935
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Horace L. Wilgus Papers 1878-1935
Wilgus, Horace L. (Horace La Fayette), 1859-1935.
86362 Aa 2; Ac
Professor of law at University of Michigan, and specialist in corporation law. Correspondence, speeches, newspaper clippings, notes, and manuscripts of books and articles, relating to his professional career, Ann Arbor, Michigan organizations and issues, particularly progressive political movements and prohibition, including the Michigan Anti-Saloon League, the anti-trust movement, and the 1912 Progressive Party; also photographs.
4.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Stanley D. Dodge (donor no. 1100 and came to the library in multiple accessions, 1940-1960.
The collection is open to research.
Horace Lafayette Wilgus, a member of the University of Michigan Law School faculty for 34 years, was born in Conover, Ohio, in 1859. After graduating in 1882 from Ohio State University with a Bachelor of Science degree, he held a variety of occupations, including deputy county surveyor in Miami County, Ohio, and instructor in mathematics at Ohio State University. In 1884, he was admitted to the Ohio Bar, and he opened a law office in Troy, Ohio, in 1886. In 1889, he earned a Masters of Science degree, also from Ohio State.
In 1890-1891, Wilgus helped to organize the law school at Ohio State, where he became secretary and professor of elementary law. In 1895, he resigned both positions to become professor of law at the University of Michigan. He was made a permanent member of that faculty in 1897.
Wilgus earned special regard for his work in torts and corporation law, and was the author of several books, including Cases in the Law of Evidence (1896), The United States Steel Corporation (1901), Annotated Cases in the Law of Private Corporations (1902), and The Law of Private Corporations (1910). He was a frequent contributor to the Michigan Law Review and other legal publications.
Following his retirement in 1929, he became professor emeritus, and in 1932, published an annotation on corporation law in collaboration with Burritt Hamilton. He died in 1935 of a heart attack.
The Horace L. Wilgus papers include correspondence, speeches, clippings, notes, manuscripts of books and articles dealing with his professional career, the many Ann Arbor organizations and issues in which he was interested: particularly progressive political movements and prohibition, including the Michigan Anti-Saloon League, the anti-trust movement, and the 1912 Progressive Party. The collection also includes University of Michigan Law School course materials, family genealogical information, and a small series of photographs, many of them of his home on Washtenaw Ave. in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
Subjects:
Agriculture.; American Federation of Labor.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.). Board of Commerce.; Ann Arbor Cattle Company.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Charters.; Ann Arbor (Mich.). Dept. of Public Works.; Ann Arbor Golf and Outing Club.; Ann Arbor Union Builders' Corporation.; Anti-Saloon League of Michigan.; Capital punishment.; Congregational churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Corporations.; First Congregational Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); First Presbyterian Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Fletcher, William Asa, 1788-1852.; Kent, Charles A. (Charles Artemis), 1835-1917.; Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), b. 1888.; Markham's Pottery Works (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Men and religion movement.; Michigan School of Religion.; Nichols Arboretum (University of Michigan); Ohio State University.; Pews and pew rights--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Presbyterian Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Prohibition--Michigan.; Progressive Party (1912); Radio broadcasting--Michigan.; Lawyers--Religious life--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Research Club.; Scott, Walter Quincy.; Taxation--United States.; University of Michigan. Alumni Association.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Class of 1904.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan. Office of Religious Affairs.; Wilgus, Horace L. (Horace La Fayette), 1859-1935.; World War, 1914-1918.; University of Michigan--Student housing.; Dormitories--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dining rooms.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Interiors.; Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Living rooms.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Law. Class of 1898.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Law. Class of 1903.; Wilgus, Horace L. (Horace La Fayette), 1859-1935.; Frieze House (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Contributors:
Adams, Charles Francis, 1835-1915.; Ames, James Barr, 1846-1910.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Bogle, Thomas Ashford, 1852-1921.; Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940.; Bradshaw, John William, 1878-; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Cooley, Lyman Edgar, 1850-1917.; Davis, R. C. (Raymond Cazallis), b. 1836.; Eaton, Amasa M. (Amasa Mason), 1841-1914.; Flexner, Abraham, 1866-1959.; Garfield, James Rudolph, 1865-1950.; Gelston, J. M. (Joseph Mills), 1847-1931.; Hudson, Joseph Lowthian, 1846-1912.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Kent, Charles Foster, 1867-1925.; Logan, Walter S. (Walter Seth), 1847-1906.; Mecham, Floyd R. (Floyd Russell), 1858-1928.; Michener, Earl C. (Earl Cory), 1876-1957.; Mosher, Eliza Maria, 1846-1928.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Patton, Carl S. (Carl Safford), 1866-1939.; Shaw, Wilfred Byron, 1881-1959.; Tatlock, Henry, 1848-1942.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1879-1880 (Box 1)
  - 1881-1885 (Box 1)
  - 1886-1890 (Box 1)
  - 1891-1895 (Box 1)
  - 1896-1900 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1901 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1901 (Box 1)
  - January 1902 (Box 1)
  - February 1902 (Box 1)
  - March 1902 (Box 1)
  - April 1902 (Box 1)
  - July-August 1902 (Box 1)
  - September-October 1902 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1902 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1903 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1903 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1903 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1903 (Box 1)
  - Jan,-March 1904 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1904 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1904 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1904 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1905 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1905 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1905 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1906 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1906 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1906 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1906 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1907 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1907 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1907 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1907 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1908 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1908 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1908 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1908 (Box 1)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
  - 1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911 (Box 1)
  - 1912 (Box 1)
  - 1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916-1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
  - 1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935 (Box 1)
- Notes, Writings, and Topical files
  - Notes on classes at Ohio State University 1878 (Box 2)
  - Thesis entitled "Taxation of American Colonies by England," 1889 (Box 2)
  - Speech entitled "The Tragedy of Thirteen Days in 1914" undated (Box 2)
  - Paper on the influence of ancient Rome on the Middle Ages (Box 2)
  - Paper on the history of the Magna Carta (Box 2)
  - Papers on the American system and women's rights (Box 2)
  - Paper on capital punishment (Box 2)
  - Paper on the proposed corporation law for Michigan (Box 2)
  - Booklet entitled "The Trust Problem" and notes 1903 (Box 2)
  - Article in the Michigan State Bar Journal entitled "The New Michigan Corporation Law-to What it Applies," 1921 (Box 2)
  - Notes on the history of corporation law (Box 2)
  - Notes on corporation law (Box 2)
  - Notes on the trust corporation (Box 2)
  - Notes on trusts and corporation law (Box 2)
  - Notes and reports on a national incorporation law (Box 2)
  - Notes and lectures on torts (Box 2)
  - Notes on arrest without warrant (Box 2)
  - Notes on master and servant and right to contract to labor and to employ labor (Box 2)
  - Notes and pamphlets on laws concerning nurses and medicine (Box 2)
  - Notes on the proposed Michigan School of Religion (Box 2)
  - Notes on the Emeritus Club (Box 2)
  - Notes on the First Congregational Church of Ann Arbor (Box 2)
  - Notes on the Proposed Ann Arbor Charter 1921 (Box 2)
  - Notes on the Ann Arbor Golf and Outing Club (Box 3)
  - Notes on the Ladies Library Association of Ann Arbor (Box 3)
  - Notes on the Ann Arbor Board of Commerce (Box 3)
  - Notes on the Ann Arbor Cattle Company (Box 3)
  - Notes on the property and continuity of the University, with deeds (Box 3)
  - Biographical sketch of Charles Artemis Kent (Box 3)
  - Biographical material on W.A. Fletcher (Box 3)
  - Lectures on law 1894-1905 (Box 3)
  - Lectures on the U.S. Steel Corporation 1901 (Box 3)
  - Lectures on law 1918 delivered before military classes (Box 3)
  - Course outlines (Box 3)
  - Tests and reports of the U of M Law School (Box 3)
  - Law Study Survey returns March 27, 1908 (Box 3)
  - Report entitled "Facts Relating to Legal Education in the U.S.," 1906-1907 (Box 3)
  - Legislation relating to uniform state laws (Box 3)
  - Legislation relating to amendment of the insurance law (Box 3)
  - Legislation relating to the regulation of the sale of stocks, bonds, and other securities (Box 3)
  - Legislation relating to the regulation of commerce (Box 3)
  - Constitution, by-laws, etc., of the Research Club 1911-1928 (Box 3)
  - Data sheets of the Research Club (U of M) 1927 (Box 3)
  - Student Christian Association
    - Statements and audits 1910-1913 (Box 3)
    - Statements and receipts 1904-1918 (Box 3)
    - Leases 1904-1911 (Box 3)
    - Ferry lectures 1905-1921 (Box 3)
    - Building 1883-1917 (Box 3)
    - Contracts 1888-1912 (Box 3)
    - Mortgages and securities 1895-1918 (Box 3)
    - Bonds 1901-1915 (Box 3)
  - Misc. materials concerning contracts and torts (Box 4)
  - Misc. materials on radio and radio regulation (Box 4)
  - Constitution of the Washtenaw County Anti-Saloon League (Box 4)
  - Manuscripts and general information on prohibition (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets on ballot reform (Box 4)
  - Campaign circulars (Box 4)
  - Pamphlets about Leonard Wood (Box 4)
  - Clippings concerning the dismissal of President Dr. Walter Quiney Scott of Ohio State (Box 4)
  - Clippings concerning President Taft and Federal Incorporation 1910 (Box 4)
  - Misc. Legal agreements (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous
  - Newspaper clippings1899-1935, 12 folders (Box 4)
  - Reprints of articles (Box 4)
  - Wilgus family genealogy charts (Box 4)
  - University of Michigan Law School notebooks, 4 volumes (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Law School material (Box 5)
- Photographs
  - Wilgus House (exteriors and interiors) 1547 Washtenaw Ave., Ann Arbor, Mich., circa 1898 (Box 5)
    (include 8 glass negatives with copyprints of some of the photos)
  - Portraits, family members, University of Michigan groups (Box 5)
    (include CD-R of most of the portraits and photos of family members)
Partial Index to Correspondence
Adams, Charles Francis, 1835-1915.
Dec. 5, 1904, Dec. 17, 1904, Feb. 20, 1906
Ames, James Barr, 1846-1910.
July 15, 1896, May 31, 1905, June 6, 1905, July 15, 1905, Dec. 8, 1905
Angell, James Burri11, 1829-1916.
Oct. 27, 1905
Baker, Newton Diehl, 1871-1937.
Jan. 11, 1912
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955
Jan. 26, 1920, Nov. 12, 1927.
Bogle, Thomas Ashford, 1852-1921.
July 25, 1907, Aug. 3, 1907, Dec. 18, 1913
Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940.
Nov. 20, 1911
Bradshaw, John W
Feb., 1902, Nov. 15, 1907
Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.
April 7, 1902
Burton, Marion LeRoy, 1874-1925.
May 7, 1929
Cooley, Lyman Edgar, 1860-1925.
July 28, 1900.
Davis, Raymond Cazalliz, 1836-1919.
April. 5, 1902, April 25, 1904
Douglas, Lloyd Cassell, 1877-1951.
Oct. 10, 1921
Eaton, Amasa Mason, 1841-1914.
April 28, 1904, May 13, 1904 July 6, 1904; Aug. 5, 1904; Aug. 18, 1904; Sept. 12, 1904, Oct. 21, 1904; Oct. 29, 1904; Nov. 3, 1904; Nov. 4, 1904
Flexner, Abraham, 1866-
Dec. 12, 1908, Dec. 22, 1908; Jan. 4, 1909
Garfield, James Rudolph, 1865-1950.
April 20, 1904, April 25, 1904
Gelston, J. Mills
Nov. 15, 1907
Hudson, Joseph Lothain, 1846-1912.
Jan. 23, 1912
Hutchins, Harry Burns, 1847-1930.
Aug. 24, 1895, Sept. 2, 1895, Sept. 13, 1895, Sept. 16, 1895, Jan. 29, 1889, April 23, 1902, April 25, 1902
Kent, Charles Foster, 1867-1925.
May 21, 1904
Logan, Walter Seth, 1847-1906.
May 13, 1904, May 25, 1904, June 1, 1904, June 10, 1904, June 13, 1904, Aug. 12, 1904
Mecham, Floyd Russell, 1858-1928.
June 24, 1904, July 20, 1904, July 31, 1904, Mar. 4, 1905, May 29, 1905, June 13, 1905
Michener, Earl Cory, 1876-1957.
Jan. 29, 1927, Feb. 26, 1927
Mosher, Eliza Maria, 1846-1928
June 5, 1902
Osborn, Chase Salmon, 1860-1949.
Dec. 28, 1911, Jan. 8, 1912, Jan. 9, 1912, Feb. 6, 1912
Patton, Carl Safford, 1866-1939.
Jan. 12, 1911
Shaw, Wilfred Byron, 1881-1959.
Feb. 2, 1905
Tatlock, Henry, 1848-1942.
Nov. 16, 1907